This video is sponsored by Factor. Get
chef-crafted, ready-to-eat meals
delivered straight to your door. Go to
factor75.com
and use code WONDERFB50 to get 50% off
your first Factor box and free breakfast
for 1 year.
In 2003, J.M. Coetzee was awarded the
Nobel Prize in literature. When giving
his acceptance speech, he didn't discuss
his career, he didn't lecture about
culture or politics, he didn't thank
anyone, he didn't even really discuss
literature.
Instead, he gave one of, if not the most
unusual Nobel Prize acceptance speeches
in history.
Following a brief reference to a
childhood memory, he proceeded to recite
a strange kind of parable. When
introducing it, he said,
"The piece is called He and His Man or
His Man and He.
I cannot remember which comes first, He
or His Man."
This was not a lapse in Coetzee's
memory. He knew the name of the story.
[music]
Fundamentally, we all live two separate
lives. One is our direct lived
experience. That is, what our bodies and
brains encounter, produce, [music] and
sense. All that is unconscious or
external, but nonetheless real and
integral to who we are.
The second is our conscious awareness.
That is, what our conscious mind
observes, comprehends, conceptualizes,
and tracks through language, ideas,
beliefs, [music] and stories.
In Coetzee's speech, he refers to two
men, He and His Man.
He is an old retired sailor who has
moved on from adventure and sea life and
now spends almost all of his time alone
in his room.
His primary interaction with the world
and others is through reports that he
regularly receives from the character
referred to as His Man,
an individual who travels around Europe
encountering various events and
phenomena.
It is soon revealed that the retired
sailor is Robinson Crusoe, one of the
most famous fictional characters in
history.
This character originated in the 1719
novel titled Robinson Crusoe, written by
the author Daniel Defoe,
in which he is an English sailor who is
shipwrecked on a remote island for 28
years before finally being rescued.
What turns Coetzee's speech from
interesting to profound, and perhaps a
bit unsettling, is that Crusoe's
correspondent, [music] his man, is
Daniel Defoe.
In other words, Defoe is sending
messages to the character he created in
the story [music]
Coetzee created.
In Coetzee's story, Crusoe and Defoe
have a strange and ambiguous kind of
relationship. On one hand, they seem to
know and depend on each other
intimately. On the other hand,
>> [music]
>> they appear to be quite unknown and
distant to each other. Neither really
know the life of the other directly.
Crusoe knows of Defoe's experiences
[music] only through his reports, and
Defoe seems to know of Crusoe, if at
all, only as a kind of receiving entity
of his reports.
Coetzee says,
"How are they to be figured, this man
and he?
As master [music] and slave? As
brothers, twin brothers? As comrades in
arms? Or as enemies, foes?
What name shall he give this nameless
fellow with whom he shares his evenings
and sometimes his nights, too, who is
absent only in the daytime,
>> [music]
>> when he, Robin, walks the keys
inspecting the new arrivals, and his man
gallops about the kingdom making his
inspections?"
There are many ways one could interpret
the premise to such an enigmatic story
and character relationship. On a
literary level, it seems to possibly be
a reflection on the relationship between
writer or artist [music]
and the characters or things they
create. What does a writer or artist do
if not report their lived experiences to
a kind of entity [music] of reception,
their work, their worlds, and their
characters?
In this, the creator feels as though
they are producing a character, story,
or [music] world, but in a way, they are
sort of already there.
That is, the character, story, or world
already exists [music] as a kind of
nebulous entity of lived experience.
They merely increasingly form into
semi-tangible structures as they receive
more information from the creator's
conscious [music] mind. A kind of
embodiment of the creator's awareness
and experience as they're assembled with
words and features. Coetzee writes,
"How then has it come about that this
man of his, who is a kind of parrot and
not much loved, writes as well as or
better than his master?
>> [music]
>> For he wields an able pen, this man of
his, no doubt of that.
Only when he yields himself up to this
man of his do such words come."
There's also a deeper interpretation
here. The very nature of the mind and
consciousness,
how we form knowledge and understanding,
and how we don't.
Whether we write or not, whether we
publish or not, each of us are authors.
Our self, the conscious observer and
narrator of our lives, is the product of
our minds' creative work. The stories we
tell ourselves about ourselves and the
world, the concepts we form, and the
beliefs we hold. Our source material,
our inspiration, is all of the
sensations of the body and brain and
their interactions with the external
world.
Naturally, these two channels,
experiencer and observer, are always
trying to work together.
Both born of and sharing the same
fundamental substrate of being, they
both operate toward the same shared
goals, survival and continuance.
On the unconscious experiential level,
this is fairly obvious. We automatically
try to catch our balance when we trip,
move our hand away from something hot or
sharp. We blink and breathe
automatically. Our heart rate
automatically increases
>> [music]
>> and we become adrenalized when we
perceive a threat, and so on.
On the conscious observer level, it's
slightly less obvious, but still
apparent. We attempt to make order,
meaning, and rigidity out of our
experiences [music]
through language, concepts, stories, and
beliefs. Our conscious mind attempts to
make sense of, tolerates, and
rationalize events so that we can best
endure and proceed onward.
Though the miracle of human
consciousness and the degree of our
conceptual awareness is perhaps only
second to the miracle of existence
itself, it is of course deeply limited.
We can only comprehend what we can
perceive, [music] and we can only
perceive what the human brain has
evolved to process.
Moreover, words and concepts are always
merely a proxy, symbols of reality and
experience, never the real things.
Thus, these two channels of experience
don't really understand each other all
that well. One is out in the world
experiencing a chaos of phenomena, while
the other is alone inside its room
trying to parse the chaos into clarity.
What is left is a kind of dissonance
between reality and consciousness.
In Coetzee's story, one of the main
reports sent back to Crusoe describes
what are known as duck decoy systems,
elaborate traps constructed to lure wild
ducks to be killed for food. Using
ponds, nets, channels, and decoy ducks,
the configurations are designed to look
natural and safe, deceiving the ducks
into moving through them until
>> [music]
>> they become trapped.
From the ducks' perspectives, they
aren't doing anything odd or unnatural.
The traps work because they look
completely real and safe to the ducks.
They see waterways, food, and other
ducks, and they simply follow their
instincts of perception.
But in the end, the pond is not real,
and the ducks become consumed.
Coetzee writes,
"By these representations, which are
made all in duck language, they, the
decoy ducks or duckoys, draw together
vast numbers of fowl and, so to say,
kidnap them.
They guide them back across the seas
from Holland and Germany and settle them
down in their decoy ponds on the fens of
Lincolnshire, chattering and gabbling to
them all the time in their own language,
telling them these are the ponds they
told them of, where they shall live
safely and securely."
Of course, we aren't ducks, but the
distance between the abilities of our
perception and the true nature of
reality is likely inconceivably further
than the distance between us and ducks.
Like the ducks in the decoy systems, we
don't misunderstand reality because
we're foolish or irrational or doing
anything unnatural. We misunderstand
reality because nature deceives us.
Reality to us is a human decoy system
constructed out of human language. And
yet its truth is entirely beyond human
language.
This interpretation maps fairly cleanly
onto several philosophical theories and
schools of thought. What is known as
transcendental idealism, originally
founded by 18th century philosopher
Immanuel Kant, argues that, in simple
terms, human knowledge is forever
limited to the appearances of things.
That is, we can never access the world
that exists outside of human perception.
The thing in itself.
Reality.
What we perceive is inextricably shaped
by the a priori structures of the human
mind.
19th century philosopher Arthur
Schopenhauer argued in his masterwork,
The World as Will and Representation,
the world is fundamentally divided into
two components.
The will,
>> [music]
>> which is the unified underlying
substrate of reality that endlessly
strives to sustain and express itself,
and representation, which is how the
world, or the expressions of the will,
appears to consciousness.
According to Schopenhauer, we can never
directly access the true reality of
things except through bodily sensations.
The body gives us a kind of access point
to the will, a direct subjective
correspondent sending us reports.
But when trying to interpret and
transcribe these reports into [music]
concepts and words, we move away from
the will and into representation,
a distortion.
Schopenhauer writes,
"The world is my representation. This is
a truth valid with reference to every
living and knowing being, although man
alone can bring it into reflective
abstract consciousness.
It then becomes clear and [music]
certain to him that he does not know a
sun and an earth, but only an eye that
sees a sun and a hand [music] that feels
an earth. That the world around him is
there only as representation. In other
words, only in reference to another
thing,
>> [music]
>> namely that which represents.
And this is himself.
Everything that exists for knowledge and
hence the whole of this world is only
object in relation to the subject,
perception of the perceiver.
In a word, representation.
Likewise, the philosophy of Taoism
suggests that the observing self,
experiencing self, and external world
are all inseparable in a state of
constant flux, carried out by what is
referred to as the Tao, the true
underlying unified nature of reality.
But as such, the Tao exists solely
beyond concepts and language. It cannot
be named or understood. Ideas and terms,
including the Tao itself, can only
gesture in its direction. Reality in
this case isn't exactly a trap, but
trying to comprehend and categorize it
is.
We must rather flow with it, letting go
of rigidity, explanations, and
certainties.
The opening verse of the Tao Te Ching
reads,
"The Tao that can be spoken is not the
eternal Tao.
The name that can be named is not the
eternal name.
The nameless is the origin of heaven and
earth. The named is the mother of myriad
things.
Thus, constantly without desire, one
observes its essence.
Constantly with desire, one observes its
manifestations.
These two emerge together, but differ in
[music] name.
The unity is said to be the mystery,
mystery of mysteries,
>> [music]
>> the door to all wonders."
In the end, Coetzee seems to possibly be
representing a similar kind of inability
to comprehend the world and define the
self through a sequence of character
relationships.
Robinson Crusoe's relationship with his
creator, Daniel Defoe, and Crusoe and
Defoe's relationship with Coetzee, who,
in this story, is sort of their creator.
In this web of fiction weaved out of
experience, it isn't obvious what and
who is real, if anything.
Referring back to Kochi's introduction
to his story, when he says, "The piece
is called he and his man, or his man and
he. I cannot remember which comes first,
he or his man."
There is something subtle, yet deeply
important in this preface that seems to
cleanly summarize the authorship problem
of identity and truth.
We imagine we are the author of our
thoughts and selves, but we are
characters being written by the reports
of forces we barely understand or have
access [music] to.
We are both a character being written
and the author of the character in the
same story. [music]
We are not solely the observing mind, we
are not solely the experiencing body,
and we are not the external world.
We are the sum total of all of it, all
in constant motion.
We are each [music] an expression of the
will, the Tao, a universal awareness,
or the universe itself, whichever word
or concept you like.
Because in the end, whichever word or
concept you like,
is irrelevant.
Of course, what is relevant to
continuing on and flowing with reality
is eating. Ironically, despite eating
being one of the most basic and
fundamental aspects of our condition,
getting and preparing good quality, good
tasting meals can be extremely
time-consuming and inconvenient. This
video's sponsor, Factor, [music] helps
solve that exact problem.
Personally, I'm not big into cooking,
and I'm someone who tries to prioritize
time and focus as well as I can.
Shopping and cooking are just not often
at the top of that list, if I can avoid
them.
>> [music]
>> The problem is, of course, alternatives
can be junk food or expensive meals out,
but Factor makes it so I can both reduce
time shopping and cooking without
compromising on taste [music] or
nutrition. Factor's meals are made with
real ingredients, have balanced macros,
and come with at least two vegetables
per meal, which makes the challenge
[music] of maintaining a balanced diet
much easier to overcome.
The meals are ready to eat, so no
planning, prep, or clean up. Just open,
heat if needed, and eat. [music]
I absolutely love the Monterey spinach
chicken I recently had, which was ready
in minutes. Particularly this time of
year, when I'm trying to maintain work
while enjoying the summer, Factor helps
me eat well with real food while
reducing stress and time [music] in a
way that is one of those things you
notice actually improves your life. 97%
of people say Factor helps them live a
healthier life, and 92% say it makes
their life [music] less stressful. I'm
certainly one of them. Head to
factor75.com
or click the link below and use code
WONDERFB50 to get 50% off your first
Factor box, plus free breakfast [music]
for 1 year. That's code WONDERFB50 at
factor75.com
to get 50% off, plus free breakfast for
1 year. Offer only valid for new Factor
customers with the code and qualifying
auto-renewing subscription purchase.
[music]
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general,
and see you next video.
>> [music]